this video is about design patterns no
not UI ux design patterns this video has
nothing to do with figma or photoshop
today we're talking about software
design patterns we will learn what they
are why you should learn them and we're
going to see an example design patterns
help us architecture and structure our
code in a way that is cleaner scalable
and easier to maintain design patterns
in software development aren't something
you can just download or copy paste into
your code design patterns are solutions
to common problems on software
development solutions to problems that
developers in all programming languages
and industries face often design
patterns are best practices that have
become sort of standardized over time
they are known across the software
industry and they also have their own
names like Builder adapter facade this
means that if you learn them the next
time you change themes or join a company
you will be able to identify what
pattern is being used and understand the
code base quicker or if you start a new
project you will build it using solid
structural foundations design patterns
fall in one of three categories
creational structural and behavioral
creational design patterns give us
object creation mechanism for multiple
situations keeping the code flexible and
reusable they are a way to make a system
independent of how its objects are
created structural design patterns focus
on how we organize and combine multiple
classes when building a larger system
while keeping it flexible and scalable
they allow you to change the parts of a
system independently from each other
behavioral design patterns are about how
different objects communicate between
each other they provide guidelines for
how objects and classes should
communicate and behave on relation to
one another if those explanations sound
very abstract don't worry we are now
going to take a look at one pattern to
actually understand how they make our
code better from the creational category
let's take a look at the Builder pattern
the Builder pattern is used when there
are multiple ways of creating an object
when we need to create an object that
has lots of options imagine that we
wanted to create a house class houses
can have so many different
configurations some have a balconies
backyard basements different room number
different toilet number Etc that means
that our class Constructor will be
something like this we would have to
pack all the options on the Constructor
which is going to look worse the more
properties we have instantiating the
class will look like this which isn't
good if we follow the Builder pattern
instead of having one fat Constructor
function we will create a builder class
and method that set each one of the
configuration options using the Builder
pattern our code will look like this we
first create a class called house that
only has default property then we create
a house Builder class that will
instantiate a house the moment it is
constructed then we have methods that
set each one of the properties of the
house and return this which is the
Builder itself finally we have a build
method that just Returns the created
house with this code next time that we
have to create a house all we have to do
is instantiate the house Builder and
call the methods that set the properties
we want our house to have that will set
the properties of the house via the
Builder and when we are done we call the
build method to get the house we just
made as you can see that looks much
better we can now create houses with all
sorts of characteristics just by calling
the methods we need without the need for
a fat Constructor or ugly coat the
Builder pattern helps makes our code
cleaner and easier to manage plus it
adds flexibility for example if we
wanted to add a new feature to our house
class tomorrow we simply add the new
feature and a method to set it up we
don't need to change or fix any other
part of our code this easy way of adding
new things without messing up the
existing code is one of the biggest
benefits of the Builder pattern I hope
that by now you sort of understand what
design time patterns are and why
learning them will help you as I said
they're just best practices that have
helped developers over many years solve
problems we all often face I don't want
to make this video too long and I don't
know how many of you are interested on
learning design patterns but if you like
this video subscribe to the channel and
comment below I will make another video
or even a series of videos where we can
learn other patterns from the structural
and behavioral categories if you like
the way I explain things and you would
like to learn things like JavaScript
python react react native go dark
flutter among many others for absolutely
free all you have to do is click the
link below to join any of our many free
courses you can take right now for
absolutely free with me click the link
below and I will see you there anjana
comes see you on the next one bye
[Music]
thank you